<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act against unlicensed and scandalous books and pamphlets, and for better regulating of printing</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39516</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12713872</idno>
  <idno type="VID">66146</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248567824</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E971</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10049</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12713872</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39516)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 689:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act against unlicensed and scandalous books and pamphlets, and for better regulating of printing</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 533-549 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Field for Edward Husband ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed by Hen. Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti. 20 Septembr. 1649.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Printing --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Press law --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66146:1"/>
            <p>AN ACT AGAINST Unlicensed and Scandalous Books and Pamphlets, And for better Regulating of PRINTING.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>coat of arms for the Commonwealth of England, 1649</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license" subtype="order_to_print">
                        <p>Die Jovis, 20 Septembr. 1649.</p>
                        <p>ORdered by the Commons assembled in Parliament, That this Act be forthwith printed and published.</p>
                        <p>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Field</hi> for <hi>Edward Husband,</hi> Printer to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:66146:2"/>
            <pb n="533" facs="tcp:66146:2"/>
            <head>AN ACT Against Unlicensed and Scandalous Books and Pamphlets, And for better Regulating of PRINTING.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHereas divers scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, seditious and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellous Pamphlets, Papers and Books are daily contrived, printed, vended and dispersed, with offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care and industry by the Malignant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at home and abroad, for the better compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of their wicked ends, The subversion of the <hi>Parliament</hi> and present Government, which they well know cannot with more ease be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, then by Lyes and false Suggestions, cunningly insinuated and spread amongst the People, and by malicious misrepresentation of things acted and done, to take off and divide their affections from that Iust Authority which is set over them for their good and safety, and to bring a low and mean esteem upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and a suspition and hatred upon the courses
<pb n="534" facs="tcp:66146:3"/> and intentions of the faithful Members of the Peoples Representative in Parliament, and of other Ministers of State, serving the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth in their several Subordinations; especially such who are most constant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientious in discharge of their Trust, and are therefore become the utmost object of their wretched spleen and malice: And whereas a great occasion of these mischiefs, and scandals, and dis-satisfaction of many, hath been as well the ignorance and assumed boldness of the week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pamphleteers, without leave or due Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, taking upon them to publish, and at pleasure to censure the Proceedings of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Army, and other Affairs of State; as also the irregularity and licentiousness of Printing, the Art whereof in this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and in all Forreign parts, hath been and ought to be restrained from too arbitrary and general an exercise: To prevent the many mischiefs inevitably following thereupon, The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> duly considering the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, and willing to apply fit remedy herein, Do Enact and Ordain, and be it by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid Enacted and Ordained, That the Laws made formerly, and at this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, now in force for punishment of devisers and spreaders of false and seditious News, Lyes and Rumors, by writing, printing, speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or otherwise, shall be put in due and diligent execution, according to the tenor of the same Acts; And for further remedy, Be it Enacted and Ordained, That no person or persons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, shall presume to make, write, print, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, sell or utter, or cause to be made, printed or uttered, any scandalous or libellous Books, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amphlets, Papers or Pictures whatsoever,
<pb n="535" facs="tcp:66146:3"/> upon the Penalties following; that is to say, The Author of such Books, Pictures or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, shall forfeit Ten pounds, or be Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Common Goal of the County or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty where the Offence is committed, or the Offender shall be found, until he shall pay the same, so that the Imprisonment exceed not forty days; The Printer to forfeit and pay five pounds, and suffer the like Imprisonment, until he pay the same, the said Imprisonment not exceeding twenty days, and likewise to have his Press and Implements of Imprinting seized, and broken in pieces; The Bookseller and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner to forfeit and pay Forty shillings, or be Imprisoned in like maner, until he pay the same, the Imprisonment not exceeding ten days. And be it further Enacted, That if any person hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to buy any such seditious, scandalous or libellous Pamphlets or Papers, and shall not within four and twenty hours after knowledge thereof, bring them to the Lord Major of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> (if the buyers resiance be there) or to some other Iustice of the Peace within the County, City or Liberty where such Buyers shall then happen to be, to be sent up, and disposed of as by this Act is afterwards mentioned, and give notice likewise of the party or parties of whom he or they had or bought the same, shall forfeit for every such omission the sum of Twenty shillings for every such concealed Paper, Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet or Book, to be disposed of as is herein after mentioned. And for the prevention of false, imperfect and impertinent Relations of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Proceedings, and other such Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and News, the truth whereof may be fit to be known and published, for the satisfaction of all the good people of this Commonwealth
<pb n="536" facs="tcp:66146:4"/> therein interessed, and of all the well-affected thereto, in the clear Information of the state of Affairs; Be it Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, That no person whatsoever shall compose, write, print, publish, sell or utter, or cause to be made, written, printed or uttered, any Book or Pamphlet, Treatise, sheet or sheets of News whatsoever, unless Licensed (as is hereafter mentioned) upon the like Penalty as upon the Maker, Writer, Printer, Bookseller and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner respectively of scandalous Books and Pamphlets, both for Fine and Imprisonment, is herein before limited and appointed. And be it further Enacted and Ordained, That the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender aforesaid shall be discovered, the Offences heard and examined, and the Penalties levied and disposed of in such sort, maner and form as is limited, directed and expressed in an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of <hi>Parliament,</hi> made in <hi>Septemb.</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand six hundred forty and seven, <hi>Against Unlicensed Pamphlets, and for the better Regulating of Printing.</hi> Provided, That so much of the said Ordinance as specifies the imposition of Penalties upon such Offenders as are before mentioned, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect that higher Penalties are in stead thereof herein limited and designed, shall stand from henceforth Repealed, and be of no further effect. And be it further Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, that all former Licenses granted by Authority of both or either House of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any person or persons, for Printing any <hi>Diurnal,</hi> News or <hi>Occurrences,</hi> shall be from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth void and of no further effect; And that no Book, Pamphlet, sheet or sheets of News or Occurrences whatsoever, shall henceforth be printed, bound, stitched or put to sale by any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons whatsoever, unless the same be
<pb n="537" facs="tcp:66146:4"/> first approved of and Licensed under the hand of the Clerk of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or of such person as shall be authorized by the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cel of State for the time being; or (for so much<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> may concern the affairs of the Army) under the hand of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of the Army for the time being, the same to be entred in their several Registers, to be by them kept for that purpose; and also in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gister-Book of the Company of Stationers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ancient custom; and the Printer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to put his hand thereto. Provided always, and it is hereby Declared, That the penalties in this Act expressed, shall not extend to quit any person or persons, that shall make, write, print, publish, sell or utter, or cause to be made, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, published, sold or uttered, any Book, Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, Treatise, Ballad, Libel, sheet or sheets of News, that shall contain any Seditious, Treasonable or Blasphemous matter, but the offenders in such kinde shall be liable to such fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther penalties, as by the Laws of the Land are provided, or by Authority of Parliament shall be judged, according to the quality of such offences. And be it further Enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That the Master and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the Company of Stationers <hi>London,</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted with such persons as the Councel of State shall for that purpose nominate or approve, shall and may make diligent search in all places where they shall think meet, for all unallowed Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-presses, and all Presses any way imployed in the printing of any such unlicensed Books, as aforesaid; or of any malignant, seditious or scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Books, Pictures or Papers, and to seize and carry away such Printing-presses and Letters, together with the Nut, Spindle, and other Materials of every such irregular
<pb n="538" facs="tcp:66146:5"/> Printer, which they finde so misimployed, unto the Common-Hall of the said Company, there to be defaced and made unserviceable, according to ancient custom; and likewise to make diligent search in all suspected Printing-houses, Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses, Shops, and other places, for such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licensed and scandalous Books, Papers, Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, and all other such Books not entred, nor signed with the Printers name, and place of resiancy, being printed or reprinted by such as have no lawful interest in them, and the same to seize; and likewise to apprehend all Authors, Printers, and other persons whatsoever, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in compiling, printing, stitching, binding, publishing and dispersing of the said scandalous and unwarrantable Papers and Books, and all those who shall assist the said parties in search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after them; and to bring the offenders, and what they shall have so seized, before such Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate or other Officers as are appointed for the execution of this Act, to be by them ordered and disposed of according to the direction and true meaning of the same Act. And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That no person or persons whatsoever, shall presume, by the Post, Carriers, or otherwise to convey, send away, or endeavor to disperse any such unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censed News as aforesaid, or any seditious or scandalous Papers, Pamphlets, Books or Pictures, to any place, or person or persons, upon pain of forfeiture of forty shillings a piece for every such Book, Pamphlet or Paper, or Imprisonment of the offender, the same not to exceed forty days; the said penalty to be inflicted, paid and undergone, the moneys to be disposed of, and such inquiry, searches and seizures touching the same to be made, as in the case of
<pb n="539" facs="tcp:66146:5"/> selling unlicensed News is herein before limited and expressed. And whereas the great numbers of lewd and scandalous Pamphlets and seditious Books, have been chiefly occasioned by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Printing-houses, and Presses erected in by-places and corners, out of the eye of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, contrary to the custom and practice of former times; and in that regard some fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther provision is held requisite for restraining and regulating that general excess and exercise of the Press, and prevention of the said Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, It is therefore further Enacted and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by this present Parliament, and by the Authority thereof, That no Printer, nor any other person or persons whatsoever, shall from henceforth print, use or imploy any Printing-press, Rolling-press, or any other Instruments for Printing, in any part or place of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, save onely in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Liberties thereof, and the two Vniversities (excepting such as shall be particularly Licensed and authorized by special Order of the Councel of State) upon pain that all and every person and persons offending contrary hereunto, shall forfeit and pay the sum of Twenty pounds, and shall have all their Printing-presses, Letters and Materials defaced, and be for ever disabled to be a Master Printer, and Owner of a Printing-press: Provided, That this Clause shall not be construed to extend to the Printing-press now used in the City of <hi>York,</hi> nor to the Printing-press now used in <hi>Finsbury,</hi> for the Printing of Bibles and Psalms; but that the same shall be in like condition to all purposes, as it this Act had not been had or made. And it be further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all and every
<pb n="540" facs="tcp:66146:6"/> Printer, or other person or persons whatsoever in the said City of <hi>London,</hi> who now keep Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-houses, or are Owners of Printing-presses, Rolling-presses, or other Instruments for Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; as also the Owners of the Printing-press in <hi>Finsbury</hi> aforesaid, shall before the First day of <hi>October,</hi> One thousand six hundred forty nine, enter into Bond, with two Sureties, of Three hundred pounds penalty to the <hi>Keepers of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of <hi>England</hi> by Authority of Parliament,</hi> Not to print, nor cause to be printed, any seditious, scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous or treasonable Pamphlet, Paper, Book or Picture, dishonorable to, or against the State and Government; nor any Pamphlet, Paper, or Book of News, not Licensed as aforesaid, and Entred in the Register Book of the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; nor suffer their Printing-presses, or other Instruments for Printing, to be used for any such unlawful purpose as aforesaid; and that he and they shall also to every Book, Pamphlet, Paper or Picture he or they shall imprint, in the Title-page of each Book prefix the Authors name, with his quality and place of Residence, or at least the Licensers names where Licenses are required, and his own Name and place of Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at length, upon pain to forfeit the sum of Ten pounds for every wilful failing, and to have all his or thiea Printing materials defaced; and for the second Offence, to be disabled from any more exercise of his Trade of Printing: And that like caution shall be given by the Owner of the Press at <hi>York,</hi> to the <hi>Keepers of the Liberties of England</hi> as aforesaid, and by the Printers within either Vniversity, to the said <hi>Keepers of the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of England,</hi> in like sum, and for like purposes, and upon like penalties for failing, as is herein
<pb n="541" facs="tcp:66146:6"/> lastly mentioned, whereof the especial care to see the same performed within the time last before limited, is especially commended to the Lord Major of <hi>York,</hi> and to the said Vice-Chancellors respectively, of which they are under their Hands and Seals to make Certificate to the Councel of State, before the Tenth day of <hi>October,</hi> One thousand six hundred forty nine. And be it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That no person or persons whatsoever, shall hereafter set up a Printing-press, Rolling-press, or other Instrument for Printing, nor cast any Printing Letters, before they enter into Bond as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said; nor shall any person or persons demise or let, or being within his or their dispose, suffer to be held or used any House, Vault, Cellar, or other Room whatsoever, to or by any person or persons for a Printing-house, or place to print in, unless he or they so demising and suffering, shall first give notice to the Master or Wardens of the Stationers for the time being, of such demises or suffering to work or print there, upon pain of forfeiture of Five pounds for every such Offence; of which intimation the Master and Wardens are hereby enjoyned to make an Entry in their Register Book, upon like pain of forfeiture of Five pounds for every omission thereof. And be it further Enacted, That no Ioyner, or Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or other person, shall make any Printing-press or Rolling-press, nor any Smith shall forge any Iron-work for a Printing-press, nor any Founder cast any Printing-letters for any person or persons whatsoever; neither shall any person or persons import, or cause to be imported or brought into this <hi>Cōmonwealth,</hi> from any parts beyond the seas, any Printing-press or presses, or any Letters
<pb n="542" facs="tcp:66146:7"/> founded or cast, nor shall any person or persons buy any such Presses or Letters for printing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less he or they respectively shall first acquaint the Master and the Wardens of the aforesaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany for the time being, for whom the same press, Iron works or Letters are to be made, forged, imported, bought or cast, upon pain of forfeiture of five pounds for every such Offence; of which intimation the Master &amp; Wardens are to make Entry in their said Register, upon like Penalty of forfeiture of Five pounds for every omission thereof. And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That no person or persons whatsoever, shall Import any scandalous or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Books, Pamphlets or Papers, upon pain of forfeiture of five pounds for every such Book, Pamphlet or Paper; nor shall any person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons land any Imported Books, at any Port or place of this Commonwealth, save onely at the Port of <hi>London;</hi> And that no Drifats, Packs, Maunds, Chests, or Fardels of Books, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by any Officers of the Customs or Excize to be opened or conveyed away, before notice given, and the same be viewed by the said Master and Wardens of the said Company, or such as they shall appoint, upon pain of forfeiture of Five pounds for every such Offence, so as the Master and Wardens or their Deputies, do make the said view within forty eight hours after such notice, which they are hereby required to make, upon pain of forfeiture of Five pounds for every omission of such view as aforesaid. And it is also Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That for the encouragement of all Regular Printers, and support of the said Manufactures in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, That no person or persons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever,
<pb n="543" facs="tcp:66146:7"/> shall from henceforth Import, or bring in, or cause to be Imported or brought into this Commonwealth, from any part whatsoever, any English Bibles, Psalms, or any Book or Books, or part of Book or Books formerly printed in this Commonwealth; nor shall binde, stitch, or put to sale, any such Book or Books, upon pain of loss and forfeiture of the same, and of Ten shillings for every Book so imported, bound, stitched, or put to sale. And be it further Enacted, That no person or persons whatsoever in this Commonwealth, shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after print or reprint any Book, Books, or part of any Book or Books, Legally granted to the said Company of Stationers, for their relief or maintenance of their poor, without the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense and consent of the Master, Wardens and Assistants of the said Company; nor any Book or Books, or part of Book or Books, now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the Register Book of the said Company, or which hereafter shall be duly entred in the said Register Book, for any particular Member of the said Company without the like consent of the owner or owners thereof, nor counterfeit the Name, Mark or Title of any Book or Books, belonging to the said Company or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular members; nor shall any person or persons binde, stitch or put to sale any such Book or Books, upon pain of forfeiture of the same, and of Six shillings and eight pence for every Book printed or stitched, bound or put to sale contrary hereunto: And for the better discovery of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Booksellers, and others, who make a trade of vending, dispersing and sending to their Customers and Correspondents in the Countrey in Packets, by the Post, Carriers,
<pb n="544" facs="tcp:66146:8"/> and such like persons, divers unlicensed and other scandalous and seditious Books, Papers, Pamphlets and Pictures, to the great abuse of the Parliament, and prejudice of the People, Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That any two Magistrates intrusted with the Execution of this Act respectively, shall have power upon any just occasion of suspition, to grant Warrants under their Hands and Seals, to some sufficient persons, to search Packs and Packets, and seize and bring away such Books, Papers and Pamphlets, to those who granted the said Warrants, to the end the Penalties may be levied upon the offenders, and disposed of according to the tenor and true meaning of this present Act. And be it Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That all unlicensed Books and Pamphlets of News, and all seditious, scandalous and libellous Books, Pamphlets, Pictures and Papers, to be seized by vertue of this Act, shall after the condemnation of the offender with whom they are taken, or to whom they belong (if the offender may be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and known) be brought, conveyed or sent, and safely delivered to the Secretary to the Councel of State, to be disposed of to the fire or otherwise, as that Councel shall direct, and be in the mean time safely preserved by the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers or persons who seize the same, or by those to whom they make delivery thereof, and give account of their imployment, according to the true meaning of this Act. And whereas di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers vagrant persons, of idle conversation, having forsaken their usual Callings, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed themselves after the maner of Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, to sell and cry about the streets, and in
<pb n="545" facs="tcp:66146:8"/> other places, Pamphlets, and other Books, and under colour thereof, are found to disperse all sorts of dangerous Libels, to the intolerable dishonor of the Parliament, and the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Commonwealth; Be it Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, That no such Hawkers shall be any more permitted; and that they and all Ballad-sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, wheresoever they are or may be apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, shall forfeit all Books, Pamphlets, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads and Papers by them exposed to sale, and shall, by such as shall by vertue of this Act seize upon them, be conveyed and carried to the House of Correction, there to be whipt as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Rogues, and then dismissed; the Keepers of which House are hereby enjoyned to receive such prisoners, and see this penalty executed, without expecting further warrant; and where no such House of Correction is, those who seize upon such offenders, shall deliver them over to the Constable of the Parish or Liberty where they are apprehended, who is forthwith to cause the offenders to be whipt as common Rogues, upon pain of forfeiture of Forty shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, to be paid by such Keepers of the House of Correction or Constable, omitting, neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or refusing to do their duty herein: The said offences in this clause mentioned to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, and the penalties levied, and to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed of in such sort and maner, as concerning the penalties of such as vend unlicensed and scandalous Books and Pamphlets, is herein before directed and expressed: And the Lord Major and Common Councel of the City of <hi>London,</hi> are hereby required to take care that the good Laws of their City against Hawkers,
<pb n="546" facs="tcp:66146:9"/> and that this present Act against them and other offenders, be put in full and speedy execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion within their City and Liberties thereof, as they tender the Honor thereof, and of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And all Constables, Headboroughs, and other Officers and Ministers, are hereby enjoyned to seize upon such last mentioned Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders wheresoever they may be found, and to cause the penalties of the Law to be upon them executed, upon the penalty last before mentioned. And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That whatsoever penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in money shall be levied and received by the pains, industry and prosecution of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Stationers (whose vigilancy and care herein is especially required) shall be disposed of as followeth; <hi>viz.</hi> After satisfaction of their charges in inquiry and prosecution, the one moyety of the residue shall be by them received and reserved for the use of the poor of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and the other moyety, or one half, for the use of the Commonwealth, to be yearly by them answered, and paid into the receipt of the publique Exchequer: And the Iustices of the Vpper Bench, Iustices of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> within the limits of their Commission, Iustices of Assize in their several Circuits, Iustices of Goal Delivery, and Iustices of Peace, as well within the Liberties as without, within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of their several Commissions in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sessions, or other Sessions, which they or any two or more of them (whereof one of them to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) may and shall appoint at their pleasure, where and when need shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, shall by vertue hereof have full power and authority, and are hereby strictly enjoyned to
<pb n="547" facs="tcp:66146:9"/> enquire, hear and determine all and every the Offences aforesaid, and to give in charge the Presentment of the same; and they and all other Officers and Ministers concerned, are hereby enjoyned and required to be careful and diligent in the discharge of their duty in the premises, according to the tenor and direction of this present Act: And all Officers Civil and Military, Soldiers, and other well-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected people, are hereby specially enjoyned to be ayding and assisting to the execution of this Act, and to seize upon the persons of all such as shall presume to rescue, or actually endeavor to rescue from apprehension or punishment the offenders against this Act, to cause such Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancers and Disturbers to be immediately brought before some Iustice of the Peace, who is to binde them by a Recognizance with good Sureties to the Good Behavior, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the next Sessions for the Peace, there to be Indicted, Fined, and further dealt with, according to Law, and as the quality of such High Contempts may deserve: And such said Offenders as are not able to finde Sureties, are to be caused to be set in the Stocks near to the place where the Offence was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and to be Imprisoned there for the space of four hours. And because the life of all good Laws, is the due execution thereof, and that the careful observance of this Act, and a strict enquiry into, and punishment of Offenders against the same, will be of especial concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Peace and safety of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That the Councel of State appointed
<pb n="548" facs="tcp:66146:10"/> by the Parliament, shall hereby have power and authority to enquire into, and from time to time to receive an accompt of all wilful defaults and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of Officers or others, who neglecting or refusing to do their duties, shall thereby obstruct the Remedies provided by this Act; and are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by enjoyned and required, by all good ways and means to remove such obstructions, and out of the penalties or otherwise, to reward prosecutors or discoverers of Offenders, and to cause this Act to be put in full and effectual execution. And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That in and upon any Action, Plaint or Suit to be brought against any Officer, or person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, for any thing by them acted or done by force of this present Act, every such Officer and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son shall and may plead the General Issue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and give this Act, and the whole special mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Evidence; and if the Verdict pass against the Plaintiff or Plaintiffs, or the Plaintiff or Plaintiffs become non-Suit, or suffer any Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance thereof, That then the Defendant and Defendants shall recover his and their dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Costs for their wrongful vexation in defence of the said Action or Suit, for which he and they shall have like remedy, as in other cases where Costs by the Laws of this Commonwealth are given to the Defendants: Provided always, and be it Enacted by the authority aforesaid, That no person or persons shall be molested or impeached for any the Offences mentioned in this Act, unless he or they be thereof accused within six moneths after his or their Offence so committed or done. Provided also, That this Act be in force, and to have continuance until
<pb n="549" facs="tcp:66146:10"/> the Nine and twentieth day of <hi>September,</hi> which shall be in the Year of our Lord, One thousand six hundred fifty and one, and no longer.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Jovis, 20 Septembr. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons assembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, That this Act be forthwith printed and published.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>